{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This ruler gained control of Burgundy in the Treaty of Madrid shortly after defeating his rival at Pavia. He won the Battle of Muhlberg against the Schmalkaldic League while attempting to halt the Reformation in Germany, but eventually allowed for some religious autonomy in the Peace of Augsburg. This ruler summoned Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms. For ten points, name this 16th century monarch who served as both King of Spain and Holy Roman Emperor.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor",
        "Carlos I of Spain",
        "Charles I of Spain, but don’t"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An aristocrat boards a train bound for this region to follow the woman he loves, a prostitute who was tricked into giving a womanizing merchant a lethal dose of arsenic. This region is the setting of the later parts of the novel Resurrection. Sonya Marmeladova travels to this region near the end of Crime and Punishment. For ten points, name this region to which Raskolnikov is exiled to complete a sentence of eight years of hard labor.",
      "answer": "Siberia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Production ceilings in this industry were upheld in Wickard v. Filburn. Workers in this industry demanded fair railroad rates after organizing as the Grange. The US imported labor for this industry via the Bracero Program. Dolores Huerta coined the slogan “si, se puede,” which was used by a union in this industry led by Cesar Chavez. For ten points, name this industry whose workers migrated to California to escape the Dust Bowl, despite claims that its plowing would lead to rain.",
      "answer": [
        "agriculture",
        "farming and other equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A thunderbird replaced a yellow version of this symbol on a red diamond as the insignia of the 45th Infantry Division, which consisted of National Guardsmen from the American southwest. This symbol, whose name derives from Sanskrit for “auspicious,” was used by the Thule Society, which supported the DAP, or German Worker’s Party. For ten points, name this four-armed symbol, common in numerous religious traditions, that was adopted by the Nazi Party.",
      "answer": [
        "swastika",
        "tetraskelion",
        "hakenkreuz",
        "hooked cross",
        "fylfot",
        "tetragammadion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the causes of this rebellion was the selective distribution of trade contracts by the Long Assembly. Thomas Larimore led a group of ships dispatched to fight this rebellion, which ended when its namesake leader died of dysentery. The perceived pro-Native American stance of governor William Berkeley incited this rebellion, whose agitators burned Jamestown to the ground in 1676. For ten points, name this first major rebellion in colonial Virginia.",
      "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "People who were not in one of these organizations revolted in Florence during the Ciompi [chomp-ee] Revolt. An alliance of these organizations formed a trading league in the Baltic Sea called the Hanseatic League. Some members of these organizations progressed from apprentices to journeymen to master craftsmen. For ten points, name these town-based medieval associations of merchants and skilled laborers.",
      "answer": "guilds"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man’s first campaign, commemorative monuments were carved in rock at the Dog River north of modern-day Beirut. Early in this leader’s reign, he defeated the Sherden sea pirates. At the Orontes River, this ruler fought the Hittite King Muwatallis in the largest chariot battle in history. This successor of Seti I constructed the temple complex at Abu Simbel and inaugurated that temple alongside his wife, Nefertari. For ten points, name this pharaoh who won the Battle of Kadesh.",
      "answer": [
        "Ramesses II",
        "Ramesses the Great",
        "Ozymandias"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this religion named James Strang established a controversial “kingdom” on Beaver Island in Lake Michigan in the mid 19th Century. A leader of this religion founded the territorial capital of Fillmore after his plans to found the state of Deseret fell through. Members of this religion were led to Nauvoo, Illinois by Joseph Smith and then to Salt Lake City by Brigham Young. For ten points, name this religion whose members founded the Utah Territory.",
      "answer": [
        "Mormonism",
        "word forms",
        "the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints",
        "LDS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A type of these items named for Rule 144 must be acquired in unregistered form. Privately held companiesuseIPOstoinitiatethesaleoftheseitems.Preferredtypesoftheseitemsgrantearlierdividends than their common form, which allows for voting rights in decisions. For ten points, name these financial instruments that are sold on namesake exchanges and which represent ownership of a corporation.",
      "answer": [
        "stocks",
        "any additional information, such as preferred stocks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1889 attempt to build a railway along this location ended when Frank Brown drowned exploring it. John Powell named this location after leading the first American expedition to its ground floor. The glass-bottomed “Skywalk” is maintained by the Hualapai tribe in this location, which was regarded as sacred by the ancestral Pueblo that first inhabited it. The Colorado River formed, for ten points, what 277-mile long canyon in Arizona?",
      "answer": "Grand Canyon"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man rented the Kennedy Farm in Maryland under the alias of Isaac Smith. Forces under this man defeated a contingent under Henry Pate in the Battle of Black Jack and killed several members of the Doyle family in the Pottawatomie Massacre. This man cut off telegraph cables and railroad lines as part of his raid on a Virginia arsenal. For ten points, name this abolitionist who was executed in 1859 for leading a raid on Harpers Ferry.",
        "answer": "John Brown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1856 Pottawatomie massacre left five people dead in this territory, which Horace Greeley described as “Bleeding” during the violent debate over whether it would enter the Union as a free or slave state.",
        "answer": [
          "Kansas Territory",
          "Bleeding Kansas"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1914, suffragette Mary Richardson slashed a Diego Velazquez painting titled for this figure. A limestone figurine titled for this figure was found near Willendorf in 1908; this figure thus names a class of Paleolithic female sculptures, despite predating this figure’s first appearance in myth by thousands of years. Praxiteles was once thought to be the sculptor of an armless sculpture of this goddess that was found on the island of Milos in 1820. For ten points, name this Roman goddess of beauty and counterpart to Aphrodite.",
        "answer": [
          "Venus",
          "Venus of Willendorf",
          "Rokeby Venus",
          "Venus de Milo",
          "Aphrodite, alone",
          "with the other additional information here, until “Roman” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Spanish artist created a replica of the Venus de Milo with Drawers and included several multi-colored versions of the sculpture in his painting The Hallucinogenic Toreador.",
        "answer": "Salvador Dal´ı"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man sought and received aid from Haitian president Alexandre P´etion in exchange for adopting an emancipation policy. This leader’s Organic Decree cemented his status as president-liberator of one polity. This politician wrote the Cartagena Manifesto shortly before leading the Admirable Campaign. After liberating his homeland at the Battle of Carabobo, this man met at Guayaquil with Jos´e de San Mart´ın. For ten points, name this Venezuelan liberator of many South American countries.",
        "answer": "Sim´on Jos´e Antonio de la Sant´ısima Trinidad de Bol´ıvar y Palacios"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bol´ıvar was the first president of this massive northern South American confederation that fell apart in 1831, just after Bol´ıvar’s death. This country shares part of its name with one of its successor countries.",
        "answer": "Gran Colombia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1864 raid on this city failed to relieve prisoners at Irving Block Prison. One of this city’s parks was hastily renamed Health Sciences Park in 2013; that park was the site of a Charles Niehaus equestrian statue overlooking a pair of graves. In December 2017, to avoid a state law banning war memorial changes on public property, this city sold two of its parks to a non-profit that then took down the aforementioned Confederate memorial and a statue of Jefferson Davis. Jim Strickland is the mayor of, for ten points, what Tennessee city on the Mississippi River?",
        "answer": "Memphis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to the 2013 signing of the aforementioned Tennessee law, Health Sciences Park was named for this Civil War general and early leader of the KKK, a Memphis native whose equestrian statue was removed from the park.",
        "answer": "Nathan Bedford Forrest"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This woman’s note in The Times convinced Isambard Kingdom Brunel to build the Renkioi facility shortly after this figure arrived at the Selimiye Barracks. While working at Scutari, this woman cut the death rate in half after implementing techniques like hand-washing. This woman’s service in the Crimean War granted her the nickname “Lady with the Lamp.” For ten points, name this British woman, often considered the founder of modern nursing.",
        "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel designed several of these structures, including the Clifton one in Bristol. Another of these structures in London incorporates two blue and white towers.",
        "answer": [
          "suspension bridges",
          "Clifton Suspension Bridge",
          "Tower Bridge"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, over 150 Wintu natives were killed during the Bridge Gulch Massacre. Lawrence Graham led an expedition into what is now this state following the Southern Emigrant Trail. Samuel Brannan amassed a fortune operating stores in this state, where Levi Strauss got his start selling dry goods. A discovery made at Sutter’s Mill triggered the migration of the “Forty-Niners” to, for ten points, what West Coast state, where population booms hit cities like Sacramento?",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another 19th century conflict against Native Americans in California took place in the Owens Valley, found east of this mountain range that includes Mount Whitney.",
        "answer": "Sierra Nevadas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s Keroman peninsula is the site of three submarine pens, two of which required subs to be taken out of the water completely. The success of Operation Cobra in this country led to the creation of the Falaise Pocket. Canadian soldiers launched the failed Dieppe Raid into this country, where hedgerows later hindered tanks during attempts to take Caen. For ten points, name this country, the site of the Normandy landings during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "France",
          "Vichy France"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ground troops during the Normandy campaign were under the command of this British general, who had earlier defeated Rommel in the North African campaign.",
        "answer": "Bernard Montgomery"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s final three string quartets were dedicated to King Friedrich Wilhelm II, and his fourteenth quartet was nicknamed for its chromatic slow introduction. This composer of the Dissonance and Prussian quartets was commissioned by Count Walsegg to write a piece that Franz Sussmayr completed after this man died partway through completing its “Lacrimosa” section. For ten points, name this Austrian composer of a D minor Requiem, a child prodigy who composed 41 symphonies.",
        "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This C major piece, Mozart’s 41st and final symphony, ends with a five-voice fugato. Johann Peter Salomon gave this piece its mythological and astronomical nickname after Mozart’s death.",
        "answer": "Jupiter Symphony"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Susan B. Anthony",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Right that Anthony and other suffragettes sought.",
          "answer": "women’s right to vote"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that guaranteed that right.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Denomination of coin on which Anthony was honored in 1979.",
          "answer": "one dollar coin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial type of dress, named for activist Amelia, that Anthony briefly wore.",
          "answer": [
            "Bloomer",
            "the Turkish dress"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State where Anthony was arrested in Rochester in 1872 and was unable to attend the Seneca Falls Convention.",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "1893 event in Chicago where Anthony served in the World’s Congress of Representative Women.",
          "answer": [
            "World’s Columbian Exposition",
            "1893 Chicago World’s Fair"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colleague of Anthony who wrote The Woman’s Bible and co-organized the Seneca Falls Convention.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth Cady Stanton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper published for four years by Anthony and the previous answer, funded by George Train.",
          "answer": "The Revolution"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Guns",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "American lobby group that advocates for gun rights, once led by actor Charlton Heston.",
          "answer": "National Rifle Association or NRA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet rifle favored by guerilla groups, the first of the Kalashnikov family.",
          "answer": [
            "AK-47",
            "Automat Kalashnikov 47"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese dynasty that invented gunpowder and fell to the Yuan.",
          "answer": "Song Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gun company, founded by Samuel, that popularized the 45-caliber revolver.",
          "answer": "Colt Manufacturing Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that used the Maxim gun to conquer Sudan at Omdurman, avenging the death of “Chinese” Gordon.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Daimyo, an ally of Tokugawa Ieyasu and Toyotomi Hideyoshi, who used arquebuses to win the Battle of Nagashino.",
          "answer": "Oda Nobunaga"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gun company whose rifle was the “Gun that Won the West” and whose family built a “Mystery House” in California.",
          "answer": [
            "Winchester Repeating Arms Company",
            "Winchester Mystery House"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "16th century Spanish formation, known as the “third,” that heavily featured musketeers.",
          "answer": "tercio"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Writing Systems",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Shang-era scholars wrote characters on oracle bones.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive rock whose 1799 discovery allowed the decryption of hieroglyphs via ancient Greek.",
          "answer": "Rosetta Stone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wedge-shaped marking system invented by the ancient Sumerians roughly six thousand years ago.",
          "answer": "cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose native language writes some loanwords in katakana, a system developed in the Heian era.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the Cyrillic script was invented in its medieval capital, Pliska, and is used in its modern capital, Sofia.",
          "answer": "Bulgaria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient Middle Eastern civilization based in Tyre whose alphabet evolved the Greek, Aramaic, and Hebrew alphabets.",
          "answer": "Phoenicians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Script used to write Mycenaean Greek, found in palaces on Knossos and deciphered in the 20th century.",
          "answer": "Linear B"
        },
        {
          "question": "System of “talking knots” used to relay messages throughout the Andes Mountains.",
          "answer": "quipu"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This military force was sponsored by Pope Sixtus V, who treated it as a crusade and gave its sponsors a subsidy. Prior to this force’s expected deployment of the Army of Flanders, its opponents were (20 pts)",
        "rallied by the Tilbury Speech. The Duke of Medina Sidonia commanded this force, which was designed to prevent interference in the (10 pts)",
        "Netherlands but was devastated at the Battle of Gravelines. Elizabethan England was targeted by, for ten points, what fleet launched in 1588 by Philip II of Spain?"
      ],
      "answer": "the Spanish Armada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1894, a scientist working at this man’s namesake institute discovered the Yersinia pestis bacteria that spreads bubonic plague. This scientist’s research into silkworm diseases helped save his country’s agriculture industry. This man also saved a (20 pts)",
        "boy, Joseph Meister, who had suffered serious dog bites, in 1885. This scientist built on the work of Edward (10 pts)",
        "Jenner to develop vaccines against anthrax and rabies. For ten points, name this French scientist whose namesake process heats food to kill harmful microorganisms in foods like milk."
      ],
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A member of this family replaced William Belknap as Secretary of War under Ulysses Grant. John F. Kennedy’s Profiles in Courage commended a senator from this family for criticizing the (20 pts)",
        "Nuremberg Trials; that senator from this family co-sponsored a 1947 labor relations act with Fred (10 pts)",
        "Hartley. The Chief Justice of the Supreme Court for almost all of the 1920s was from this family. For ten points, name this Ohio family of Alphonso and Robert, as well as William Howard, who succeeded Theodore Roosevelt as president."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Taft family",
        "Alphonso Taft",
        "William Howard Taft",
        "Robert Taft"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a battle for this city, camels strapped with flaming haystacks were ordered to charge in order to scatter enemy elephants. The Battle of Karnal paved the way for an attack on this city, leading the (20 pts)",
        "Peacock Throne to be carried off by Nader Shah in 1739. An earlier sack of this city was carried out by (10 pts)",
        "Tamerlane in 1398. For ten points, name this seat of the Mughal Empire, a city whose “New” district now hosts the government of Narendra Modi as the capital city of India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Delhi",
        "New Delhi after “’New’ district” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man called off the CODESA negotiations after the Boipatong massacre, carried out by members of the Inkatha Freedom Party. Quartus de Wet oversaw a trial in which this man declared “I have cherished the ideal of a democratic and free society [...] it is an ideal for which (20 pts)",
        "I am prepared to die.” This man was “Accused #1” in that 1963 trial, which was held in Rivonia. (10 pts)",
        "F.W. de Klerk released this man from prison in 1990; four years later, this man won the presidency in his country’s first post-Apartheid elections. For ten points, name this first black President of South Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist sang “It don’t take too much high IQ’s to see what you’re doing to me” in her appearance in the original Blues Brothers film. This singer, who performed “My Country, ‘Tis of Thee” at the (20 pts)",
        "2009 inauguration of President Obama, received the Presidential Medal of Freedom in 2005 for a career that included 11 Grammys for Best Female (10 pts)",
        "R&B Vocal Performance. For ten points, name this “Queen of Soul” whose hits include “Think,” “Chain of Fools,” and “Respect.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Aretha Franklin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Josef Terboven helped run this country during its Nazi occupation. The Nazi invasion of this country was discovered after the sinking of the Rio de Janeiro off the coast of (20 pts)",
        "Lillesund; during that invasion, a failed coup in this country was announced over the radio, the first such event in history. The Nazi invasion of (10 pts)",
        "Denmark was simultaneous with the invasion of, for ten points, what Scandinavian country where a pro-Nazi puppet government was led by Vidkun Quisling west of Sweden?"
      ],
      "answer": "Norway"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s death was indirectly caused by the publishing of Charles D. Cooper’s letters. James Callender wrote about this man’s affair with Maria [mah-RYE-uh] (20 pts)",
        "Reynolds. This man, who urged consolidation of state and federal debt in his “First Report on Public Credit,” joined George (10 pts)",
        "Washington to put down a rebellion in Pennsylvania over a whiskey tax that this man implemented. The First Bank of the United States was founded by, for ten points, what first Secretary of the Treasury who was killed in a duel with Aaron Burr?"
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
    }
  ]
}